<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Modesty and faithfulness in opposition to envy and rashness</title>
            <author>Jones, James, fl. 1683-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47051</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J957</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R228697</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12576316</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12576316</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63584</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47051)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63584)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 962:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Modesty and faithfulness in opposition to envy and rashness</title>
                  <author>Jones, James, fl. 1683-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Malthus,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to James Jones. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63584:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Modeſty and Faithfulneſs</hi> In Oppoſition to Envy and RASHNESS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Proverb. 22.15.</bibl>
                  <p>Fooliſhneſs is bound up in the Heart of a Child, but the Rod of Correction ſhall drive it out.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. <hi>John Child.</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis is to let you know that I met with a Childiſh wandering Pamphlet full of Pernitious matter, the Perſon who is the Author hath not put his Name unto it, but I am Informed he had more mind to have <hi>J. J.</hi> then <hi>J. C.</hi> put unto it: I am perſwaded you have been former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly much acquainted with him, therefore call to mind things, and Perſons, and do not forget your SELF, and there is great Reaſon to conclude that if the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> of it had been 25 years ago told that he ſhould put forth ſuch a Pamphlet he would have been ready to ſay as <hi>Hazael</hi> did, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.13. <hi>Is thy Servant a dog that he ſhould do this thing.</hi> The title in ſhort is a ſecond <hi>Argument</hi> for Non-Conformiſts to take the Sacrament of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but indeed I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find any thing of Argument in that Pamphlet, for the matter propoſed, and believe that the moſt wiſe ſober and ſubſtantial men of the Church of <hi>England</hi> will hardly think ſuch to be right members of the ſaid Church, who ſhall be brought to conform by no better Arguments or Conſiderations then is contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the aforeſaid Pamphlet, and though the Author hath <hi>not</hi> put his name unto it, he may be eaſily known by his Communication in it, and truly I think I may ſay without wronging the Author, that the matter contained in the ſaid Pamphlet doth diſcover him to be ſuch a man, as Chriſt ſpeaks of, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.43,44,45. <hi>viz. A man out of whom went an unclean Spirit, who wandred about and found no rest,</hi> and in Proceſs of time Returned to his houſe, and found it empty, ſwept and Garniſhed, and took with him ſeven other Spirits more wicked then himſelf, and they dwelt there, and ſo the laſt ſtate of that man is worſe then the firſt, and truly Sir upon a further conſideration of the aforeſaid Pamphlet, I find cauſe to conclude the Author, to be ſuch a man as Wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaketh of, <hi>Proverbs.</hi> 26.25,26, <hi>When he ſpeaketh fair, believe him not: for there are ſeven Abominations in his heart, Whoſe hatred is covered by deceit, his Wickedneſs ſhall be ſhewed before the whole Congregation.</hi> Sir, I know you have been concerned in the Conſideration of Numbers as Expreſſed in the Holy Scriptures, I pray Sir, ſet your thoughts at Work about theſe before mentioned Numbers, <hi>viz.</hi> Seven Abominations in a mans heart ſpoken by wiſe <hi>Solomon,</hi> and ſeven Wicked Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63584:2"/> ſpoken by Chriſt who is greater then <hi>Solomon,</hi> and let this matter be ſo Conſidered and Improved by you as may be for your Edification, but it may be you will inquire what ſhould be the Reaſon of applying the forementioned Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to the Author of the aforeſaid Pamphlet, unto which I anſwer, Firſt it doth ariſe from that Account I have of the Perſon who though he hath not put his Name to his Pamphlet, yet there be ſome In the World who know me, and do alſo very well know him, and the Account of him is as followeth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That he hath been a Profeſſor of Chriſtianity in the way of Separation from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> about thirty years.—2dly, That he was baptiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Profeſſion of Faith and Repentance, and ſo joined in Fellowſhip with a People called Baptiſs, himſelf judging Infant ſprinkling to be mans invention, and not Chriſts Inſtitution. 3dly. He did ſo grow in underſtanding of the Holy Scriptures that in a little time he was a man of Name, and Fame, conſidered as a Preacher in <hi>Bedfordſhire, Buckinhamſhire,</hi> and <hi>Harfordſhire,</hi> 4thly. He hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in Print highly Vindicating the aforeſaid Profeſſion, and practice and has been ready to undertake publick Diſputations, againſt any that Oppoſed what he Profeſſed. 5thly In Proceſs of time from being very poor, he began to grow wealthy and then he decayed in his Chriſtianity, and made ſome change of his former Principles though ſtill in the way of Separation.—6thly. He removed from the Country to the City, and joined himſelf with a very worthy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of faithful Chriſtians, where the pure Word of God was preached, and the Ordinances of God were duely Adminiſtred; who alſo were a numerous Wealthy and Bountiful People, but it ſeems that they did not find any Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary need of this new Members Aſſiſtance, ſo as to employ him and ſettle him in the Work of the Miniſtry, though their Paſtor was newly dead, howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver there was another ſmaller Church of good Chriſtians that had more need of help, and as they did partake of his Spirituals he did partake of their Temporals; ſufficient for that pains that he took amongſt them, but they did not ſee cauſe to continue him as their conſtant publick Preacher, and ſo they parted; but this was not done by that Congregation to ſave their Mony as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a covetous People, for they do now allow a Maintenance to a deſerving man, who is well known to be an able preacher and a great Schollar.—7<hi>thly.</hi> Thus things not ſuting with the mans temper, or rather his Diſtemper, he ſoon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Wandering Star, ſometimes two Meetings, and ſometimes to Church, and now a time of ſuffering is come upon the poor Proteſtant Diſſenters this poor man is all for Conformity knowing very well that the Profeſſion of Religion is much cheaper in the Church of <hi>England</hi> over what it is like to be among the Perſecuted Diſſenters, O Excellent and Stupendious Policy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> I now come to ſhew that the words of Chriſt concerning the ſeven Wicked Spirits, and the Words of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lomon</hi> concerning the ſeven Abominations in a mans heart, may be fitly applyed to the Author of the aforeſaid Pamphlet, by conſidering the bad matter contained therein, from the title page to the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis of the ſaid Pamphlet which is ſtuffed full of abominable things, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt of Nonſence. 2dly. Of Falcity, 3dly. Of Abſurdity: 4thly. Of Envy. Fifthly. Of Railery. Sixthly. Of Forgery. Seventhly. Of Hypocriſie, demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as followeth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Non-ſenfe ſheweth it ſelf to the World with a brazen Face in the very title of the ſaid Pamphlet calling or ſtiling it a ſecond Argument, when as the firſt is not Extant; being not yet in Print, truly Sir if the Author hath thus coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Children. <hi>viz.</hi> hath called and Recorded his firſt born, the ſecond child I think I may ſay to him O Excelling and Stupendious folly, what has the man a mind to turn child indeed? or is he ſtudying how to change the common ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63584:3"/> of <hi>England</hi> by making a new book of Arethmetick, ſurely if he can reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on no better the Biſhop of <hi>Ely</hi> will not be his Imprimatur. <hi>Secondly.</hi> Great Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city is in the ſaid Pamphlet for in the Title Page are theſe Words, <hi>The Root and Foundation of the Popiſh Plot further diſcovered,</hi> I muſt confeſs this was a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing way to make the book ſell, eſpecially conſidering that the Popiſh Plot is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt loſt, and people in general are very deſirous to have ſome new and further demonſtration of it, but behold a baſe cheat put upon thoſe that buy the book, for there is no mention of the Popiſh Plot, it is not ſo much as named in all the pages, neither the <hi>Root nor the Branches,</hi> upon firſt ſight of the Title, there is cauſe given to conclude that a new Evidence was riſen up for the good of the King and Kingdom who could out-do all the former Evidences about the Popiſh Plot in diſcovering the very root of it: O Excellent and Stupendious ſham, and now I will enter upon the Conſideration of the Pamphlet it ſelf, &amp; in the begining I find the Author declaring himſelf like a <hi>Prince</hi> or ſome great <hi>Prelate,</hi> Page. 1. It hath been our endeavour to correct ſome of the extravagant ſtrains found in many well meaning Diſſenters, <hi>viz.</hi> by good Arguments and Examples, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a ſight of their folly in being debar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of the Civil Rights, and the cloſe Concurrency of Penal Proſecution, they have been at laſt prevailed upon to come to Church, now what theſe good Arguments were, and whether the ſecond was before the firſt, and what thoſe Examples were, they are not viſible to me, but the injoyment of Civil Rights with the cloſe Concurrency of Penal Proſecutions I do now well underſtand, and do believe that the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> will rather count ſuch a perſon a Baſtard then a true Child, who ſhall conform upon ſuch baſe conſiderations, as to comply with the matters of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity upon the account of outward ſafety, and in page the ſecond, the Author go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on and ſaith, that it hath been the work of our Adverſaries for a long time to put the Proteſtant Clergy upon Perſecuting, thereby to juſtify their old ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed Cruelty, and in this page ſaith theſe Adverſaries, do influence and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the poor ſimple Diſſenters that Perſecution is an infallible mark of an Antichriſtian Church, now who theſe Adverſaries be that is not plainly ſaid, however this Author doth venture to give them a miſtical name, <hi>viz.</hi> the Sons of <hi>Leviathan,</hi> and truly I cannot at all think, he meaneth the people of <hi>Morocco,</hi> but there is good ground to conclude he meaneth the Papiſts, and if ſo, I believe the <hi>Church,</hi> eſpecially the Proteſtant <hi>Clergy</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> will not think that he hath done them any kindneſs to declare them to be influenced by the Papiſts to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute their Fellow Proteſtants, and ſo are but the Popes Drudges and it is baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſinuated as if there were a Confederacy between the Papiſts and the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <hi>Clergy, which I do not at all believe,</hi> and it is alſo as baſely inſinuated that the Proteſtant Diſſenters are influenced by the Papiſts to maintain their Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, whereas it is well known that the Proteſtant Diſſenters in general are wholly ſtrangers to that Party, and Deteſters of their Principles and Practices: and in page the fourth, the aforeſaid Author preſumeth to declare all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation, of which he could never yet learn more than theſe four, <hi>viz,</hi> page the third, Firſt the learning of a good Catechiſm to aid and conduct their faith, 2dly, a good and well compoſed Form of Prayer to diſcharge their devotion, 3dly, To hear learned and good men <hi>Preach</hi> to revive and quicken them to duty, 4thly, To ſquare and Regulate their Lives by Moral Precepts or the Law of nature; the which whoſoever ſhall humbly and carefully obſerve con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly and Conſcientiouſly perform, then this bold undertaker doth declare as followeth, we will aſſure them Salvation, and undertake to anſwer to God for them and be content to ſtand chargeable with their Blood if they miſcarry—Unto which particulars I reply as followeth.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:63584:4"/>
            <p>Firſt, A man may learn a good Catechiſm ſo as to underſtand all the Queſtions and Anſwers therein, and may have the right notion of all thoſe truths in his head, and yet be without the real poſſeſſion of them in his heart. 2dly, A man may have a well compoſed Form of Prayer to diſcharge his devotion, and yet be without the Spirit of Prayer, 3dly. A man may hear Learned and good men Preach to revive and quicken them to Duty, and yet be without the Word of God in the power and demonſtration of the Holy Ghoſt. 4thly, A man may ſquare and regulate his life by Moral (Precepts or the Law of Nature) humbly Carefully Conſtantly and Conſcientiouſly, and yet be without Spiritual Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and Chriſt ſaith, <hi>without Regeneration there is no Salvation, John</hi> 3.3,5.—And now for the ſaid Author ſo boldly to aſſure men of their Salvation, and undertake to anſwer to God for them, &amp; be content to ſtand chargeable with their Blood, if they miſcarry (upon thoſe four things before propoſed,) I am at a loſs what to conclude concerning the man, only this I will venture to ſay he bids fair for the Care and Cure of Souls.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Abſurdity is Contained in the ſaid Pamphlet, for he pretendeth to ſrame Arguments, and draw Concluſions from them to ingage perſons who are Diſſenters to come to the Sacrament in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but inſtead of making ſound and weighty Arguments, that may convince mens judgments, they are but very pittiful Images of Arguments, not of Gold, or Silver, or Wood as made by an Artis, but more like Images of Clay made by a Child, that bedaubs and fouls his Fingers in ſo doing—Which briefly take as followeth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To Communicate in the Supper is either a Civil or a Spiritual thing, if Civil as ſuch it may be done. 2dly, It is Commanded by the Laws of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. 3dly, 'Tis no natural Injury to our Neighbours, therefore can be no real hurt or prejudice to his own Soul,—This is a cunning and baſe inſinuation of a Corrupt Notion to Repreſent the Holy Communion as a Civil action, if this once take upon mens minds being willing to ſave themſelves from Sufferings by Penal Laws, farewel to the right performance of Holy Ordinances,—<hi>From theſe Carnal Reſonings,</hi> Firſt, if I go to the Sacraments, I ſhall not be ſo obnox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious among my Neighbours. 2dly, <hi>There is very good Neighbourly Sociiety in Eating and Drinking</hi>—3dly, <hi>The Laws of my Country doth require it</hi> 4thly, <hi>If I do it but ſeldom I ſhall eſcape Sufferings.</hi>—5thly, <hi>I ſhall hereby be qualified to maintain my Civil Rights and Priviledges</hi> and thus the Ordinance of God, the Word of God, and the Law of the Land is moſt abominably abuſed, for the Law of the Realm doth Require, them that come to the Sacrament, to come to it not as to a Civil Action, but as to Gods Holy Ordinance humbly and devoutly, and the Miniſter is to lay before the people the danger and indignation which God hath threatned to them which ſhall preſume to receive the ſame un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, ſee the Statute <hi>Anno primo Edward</hi> the ſixth Chap. the firſt.</p>
            <p>Then the Author goeth on thus page the fourth. If it be ſpiritual goodneſs it cannot be dangerous and unſafe, becauſe we have the Word of God that preſſes to whatſoever is good, if it be ſpiritual wickedneſs then it lies either in the matter made uſe of, or in the manner of Adminiſtration in the exceſs and defect of the matter or in the deſigns of the thing, but wickedneſs lyeth in none of theſe, therefore is not ſpiritual wickedneſs,—2dly, If it be ſpiritual wickedneſs, then the higheſt Acts or Inſtances of the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> goodneſs is poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive wickedneſs, if ſo what became of all thoſe that have dyed in this Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.—3dly, That part of this Kingdom that bears the denomination of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is either the Church of God, or it is the Synagogue of the Devil, if it be the Church of God it cannot be unſafe and hazardous to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63584:5"/> with it in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper—4thly, He that ſhall Communicate with the good Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhall certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Communicate with as good men as any under the Copes of Heaven referring to the <hi>Clergy</hi> for Excellency of natural Parts, profoundneſs of Learning, Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Temper, Generoſity of Principles, moſt admiral <hi>Sermons</hi> Holineſs of life largeneſs of Charity we challenge the whole Earth to over match them—<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto which particulars I do humbly and modeſtly Reply as followeth.</hi>—Firſt that the Sacrament conſidered as Gods Holy Ordinance is a ſpiritual goodneſs where ever it is Adminiſtred according to Gods Word, and yet it may be unſafe and dangerous for many particular perſons to partake of it—Firſt if they themſelves be not fit for it and their own Conſciences condemn them as unfit perſons, then it is unſafe and dangerous, and if they come to it they cannot enjoy the comfort of it, and the Word of God as alſo the Law of the Realm will condemn them that come to it unworthily.—2dly. If others as fellow Communicants are not fit for it, being known to be Perſons of unholy hearts and profane lives, then it is unſafe and dangerous for the Godly to partake with the Ungodly, for Gods Church ought to be a pure Lump in point of their Memberſhip, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6,7,13. Gods good Ordinances muſt be attended upon and Performed, by a People of good hearts, and good lives; or elſe both the Perſons and the performances may be Rejected of God, O lay it to heart. <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 1.11. <hi>To what purpoſe is the Multitude of your Sacrifices unto me ſaith the Lord.</hi> Verſ. 12. <hi>When you come to appear before me who hath Required this at your hand.</hi> Verſ. 13. <hi>Bring no more vain Oblations, Incenſe is an Abomination unto me,</hi> Verſe. 14. <hi>Your New Moons and your appointed Feast my Soul hateth, they are a trouble unto me, I am weary to bear them,</hi> Verſe. 15. <hi>When you make many Prayers I will not hear you,</hi> Verſ. 16. <hi>Waſh you, and make you Clean, put away the Evil of your doings from before mine Eyes, ceaſe to do Evil,</hi> Verſ. 17. <hi>Learn to do well ſeek Judgment, Releive the Oppreſſed Judge the Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, plead for the Widow, and all this was ſpoken to</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Conſidered as Gods Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Church,</hi>—Secondly, The Author of the ſaid Pamphlet, In the next place taketh pains to prove that the Sacrament is not Spiritual Wickedneſs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it may be ſubmitted to, and received by the Diſſenters, truly this pains may well be called the labour in vain, becauſe the Preachers of the Diſſenters and the Diſſenters in general, do acknowledge that the Sacrament as it is adminiſtred in the Church of <hi>England</hi> is right in Reſpect of thoſe particulars by which he demonſtrateth that it is not Spiritual Wickedneſs.—Firſt, they acknowledge, it is Right in the Matter. <hi>viz.</hi> Bread and Wine. Secondly, in the manner of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, <hi>viz.</hi> with ſolemn Prayers and Thankſgiving. 3dly. In the deſign, <hi>viz.</hi> a thankful Remembrance of the bleſſed Sacrifice of a dear Redeemer, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, it may be unſafe and dangerous for the Diſſenters to come to it at ſuch times in ſuch places &amp; with ſuch Adminiſtrators &amp; Communicants as their tender Conſcience is not ſatisfied with, let that Word be well conſidered, <hi>Romans</hi> 14.23. <hi>And he that doubteth is damned: If he eat becauſe he eateth not of Faith for whatſoever is not of Faith, Is Sin.</hi> From whence I thus reaſon if inferior eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and drinking be ſo dangerous when perſons are not ſatisfied in their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence about it, O how much more dangerous is Superiour Eating and drinking, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as the Sacrament is when it is done doubting and not in Faith, howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſuch of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as are Conſcientiouſly ſatisfyed. Firſt, In the Ordinance it ſelf. Secondly, In their own ſelves. Thirdly, In the fitneſs of their fellow Communicants after all due Examination, I do aſſure you I will not condemn them in Religious practice, now have any uncharitable thoughts of any Godly Perſons that have dyed in this Communion, and I do believe this is the Sentements of the Diſſenters in general.—Thirdly, the Author further ſaith, That part of this Kingdom that beareth the denomination of the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:63584:6"/> is either the church of God or the Synagogue of the Devil; if the Church of God, it cannot be hazardous, and unſafe to communicate with it in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords ſupper.</p>
            <p>A ſew Queries upon this, Firſt, What hath the man a mind to devide the church of <hi>England,</hi> and reduce it to a ſmall part of the Kingdom, and not tell which that is, and is it not well known that the whole Kingdom is the church ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law, except ſuch as were never baptized, or ſuch as are Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, which are very few, compared to this great Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query.</hi> 2. What ſtrange Monſtrous Fiſh: <hi>viz. Aleviathan</hi> did ſwim in the mans brains, to conclude, that if the Church of <hi>England,</hi> were not the church of God it muſt needs be the Synagogue of the Devil, but I perceive he had the wit or elſe by excedent he hath forborn to ſay, between theſe is, no medium, the 3. <hi>Query</hi> or did the man think by ſo expreſſing himſelf, he ſhould ſcare all men from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering his Pamphlet for fear of danger. <hi>Query.</hi> 4. Or did this man cunningly or baſely lay a Trap, and a ſnare, thinking to provoke ſome perſon to ſpeak un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reverent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of the Church and of the Sacrament, and as a cunning Watcher who knew where he had laid the Snare ſteal out, and catch the Prey, but I would have the Author of that Pamphlet to know that long ago, I have read in a good Old Book calld the Holy Bible, theſe following Words, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5,26. <hi>For among my People are found Wicked men, they lay wait as he that ſetteth Snares they catch men,</hi> and ſo being fore-warn'd I thank God I am fore-arm'd, and ſo will return to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Pamphletter, in his aſſerting that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is either the <hi>Church</hi> of God or elſe it is the Synagogue of the Devil, which I think to be a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſad deſperate and Uncharitable conclution, and therefore let it be ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> What is the church of God in the ſence of the new Teſtament.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I find it to be a company of perſons whether few or many, who are converted to God by the Word and Spirit of God, of this we have plentiful proof, in the Scriptures, thoſe that were converted as being turned from darkneſs to light, from the Power of <hi>Satan</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and ſo of <hi>Sinners</hi> made <hi>Saints,</hi> by the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, were called the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and of <hi>Christ,</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in <hi>Samariah,</hi> in <hi>Antioch,</hi> in <hi>Corinth,</hi> and many other places. Secondly, I find the Church of God to be ſuch as were baptized in Water, for Water Baptiſm was always previous to Church communion, at the Lords Table, thus it was in the primitive Church, <hi>Act.</hi> 2 41.42. After convertion then followed Water Baptiſm, and ſo Church com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. Thirdly, I find that beſides convertion and Water Baptiſm, there muſt be a Congregating together by a loving Agreement, and free conſent of the mind of each party, from a Principle of Love to <hi>God,</hi> and love to each other, without any force or Compultion, for Chriſt hath not made any penal Laws, ſuch as fines or Impriſonment to bring perſons to his Church and Ordinances, and let this be conſidered, that conformity to Gods own Worſhip, by compultion is not right <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> becauſe the conformity is to man and not to <hi>God.</hi> 4thly, When thus congregated together holineſs of converſation muſt be maintained by every particular perſon, or elſe they will be unfit for <hi>Church Communion,</hi> thus have I humbly offered my Opinion and Apprehenſion as a deſcription of a true <hi>Church God</hi> in the World, which in the ſum and ſubſtance of it neither the Diſſenters nor the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> will diſown, &amp; yet it may be that both the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> &amp; ſome congregations of Proteſtant Diſſenters, may not give their Aſcent and conſent to every particular as before expreſſed concerning the true church of <hi>God</hi> as a true deſcription of it, however this matter conſidered amongſt the Diſſenters as differing one from another, or conſidered in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as differing from the Diſſenters, it looks to much like the Devil, to conclude of, or call each other the Synagogue of the Devil, for whether one or other or whether any of them at all, have all the Eſſentials of a true church, according to the primitive
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63584:7"/> conſtitution yet ſo far as any of them in their particular perſons, and in their publick Aſſemblies do maintain godlineſs among themſelves, and promote it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others, they ought to conclude and deem each other as chriſtian Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and not Synagogues of the Devil. Fourthly, the aforeſaid author goeth on further and ſaith, in his childiſh way of arguing, he that ſhall communicate with the good members of the church of <hi>England,</hi> ſhall certainly communicate with as good men as any is under the copes of Heaven, for if we refer to the clergy, then for Excellency of Natural parts, Profoundneſs of Learning evenneſs of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, generoſity of Principles, moſt admirable Sermons and Doctrines, holineſs of life and largneſs of charity, we challenge the whole Earth to over-match them, now from the foregoing matter, conſider theſe following things. Firſt, he ſpeaketh of communion with the good Members of the church of <hi>England,</hi> and as <hi>good</hi> as any under the copes of Heaven, which words doth intimate that the reſt are bad Members, and it may be as bad men as any under the copes of Heaven.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, Conſider who theſe good Members and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>per excellent men of the Church of <hi>Eagland</hi> are.—Firſt negatively, not the brave Proteſtant Nobility.—2dly, Not the Gentry.—3dly, Not the good Church-men of the City.—4thly, Not the good Church-men of the Country, but he fixeth upon the Clergy.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly Conſider the Author of the aforeſaid Pamphlet, would fain have all perſons to whom his Pamphlet may come believe or ſuppoſe that he is well acquainted with all the Clergy in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and is thereby able to be an Evidence of their excelling goodneſs which ſeems to be a cunning intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to ſome Eccleſiaſtical Function.—4thly, Conſider that the aforeſaid Author has been a greater Traveller then he mentioneth in page 10. <hi>viz.</hi> to the utmoſt Mountains, for in this page 7. he ſpeaketh of the Dominions of the whole Earth under the Copes of Heaven, and doth challenge the whole Earth to over match the Engliſh Clergy, what would the man have thoſe that read his Pamphlet believe that he has travelled with him that ſpake boldly to God in Job. 1. verſe 7. <hi>Going to and fro in the earth, and walking up and down in it.</hi> As if he were Obſervator of the Univerſe, I will not ſay to be a guide but to give a trancendent Character of the Engliſh Clergy, but truly I think it beſt to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to all the Pariſhes in <hi>England</hi> to give a character of their particular Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy-men, they being beſt acquainted with their Natural Parts, their Temper. Principles, Sermons, Charity and Converſation, and let them judge whether they be ſo good as none better can be expected till <hi>Elias</hi> cometh with extraordinary Revelation to reſtore all things, however I do believe in my conſcience that ſome of the <hi>Clergy</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are Holy, Humble and charitable men, and that take delight in Gods Bleſſing, their Labours in mens Converſion and hate Perſecution of any of the Kings Subjects by Penal Proſecution, they well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that forced <hi>Conformity</hi> is not like to the Laſting, pray conſider well the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt</hi> Plea for the Nonconformiſt, and I do not queſtion but believe that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Gentleman hath ſome brethren like himſelf, Sons of the Church of <hi>England</hi> 5thly, The Author ſtill goeth on and reaſoneth page 8. if it be dangerous and unſafe to Communicate with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> it is becauſe ſhe is no Church at all, or at beſt but an Antichriſtian Church, unto which I Reply.</p>
            <p>Firſt, There is no neceſſity to conclude the one or other concerning the Church of <hi>England,</hi> what has the man a mind to wheadle ſome unwary perſons into dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and ſet the Diſſenters and the Church of <hi>England</hi> at a greater variance than they are, by drawing and defending ſome dangerous concluſion concerning the Church, 2dly, Surely the man hath forget or hath not well conſidered the good old Proverb, all is not gold that gliſters, ſuppoſe upon ſight of a piece of Mettle a man ſhould affirm, if it be not pure gold it muſt at beſt be braſs, another man of better underſtanding in the Mettle may affirm it is neither pure gold nor braſs, and upon bringing it to the touchſtone may find it to be a mixt Mettle.—3dly.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63584:8"/> If it ſhould be granted that the Church of <hi>England</hi> were as true and good a Church as the Church at <hi>Corinths,</hi> yet it may be as unſafe and dangerous to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the Communion in the one Church as it was in the other, <hi>viz.</hi> perſons may in Communicating, Eat and Drink their Damnation 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27,28. And now from the whole of what the Pamphleteer hath ſaid in his arguings and concluſions concerning <hi>Conformity,</hi> it may be properly ſaid unto him, O Stupendious Obſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity! For all that he hath ſaid may be argued over again to perſwade and prove that the Members of the <hi>Church of England</hi> ought to take the Sacrament amongſt the Diſſenters, and then let it be conſidered what ſervice this man hath done the <hi>Church of England</hi> I will only except one thing, <hi>viz.</hi> The want of a Penal Law to force perſons to it, briefly thus.</p>
            <p>Firſt the Sacrament conſidered as a Civil thing as ſuch it may be done, becauſe no where forbidden by God, neither is it any natural injury to a mans neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, page 4.—2dly, If it be ſpiritual goodneſs, it cannot be unſafe and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, becauſe we have the Word of God, that preſſes to whatſoever is good, page the fourth, 3dly, becauſe it is not ſpiritual wickedneſs, firſt in the matter of it page the fifth, <hi>viz.</hi> Bread and Wine that being innocent and harmleſs and fitly agreeing to Divine Inſtitution, 2dly, Not in the manner, becauſe it is ſolemnly performed with Holy Prayers and Thanksgivings with no ſmall degree of ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and gravity, 3dly, Not in exceſs or defect, becauſe none are allowed rudely to take it themſelves to eat unto gluttony, or drink unto drunkenneſs, 4thly, Not in the deſign of it, becauſe all that is propoſed in it, is a due preparation for it, and a Thankful Remembrance of the Bleſſed Sacrifice of a Dear Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and therefore if no evil in all theſe, we challenge the whole world to ſhew any formal or poſſitive wickedneſs as the Sacrament is amongſt the Diſſenters: Fourthly, Surely if the higheſt Acts of goodneſs amongſt the beſt Diſſenters be down right ſpiritual wickedneſs, <hi>viz.</hi> Preparing perſons for a Right Receiving the indeavouring to ſtrengthen mens faith thereby, and to increaſe and continue brotherly love, then the beſt Diſſenters muſt be all wicked men, which if I miſtake not ſuch a Dogmatical Concluſion is the higheſt violation of Chriſtian Charity under Heaven, page 6.—Fifthly, The Diſſenters are either the Church of God, or either the Synagogue of the Devil, If the Church of God, it cannot be unſaſe to Communicate with them in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, becauſe it is a Holy Rite truely Appropriated to the Church of God, but if they be indeed the Synagogue of the Devil, let it demonſtratively appear page ſix, and we will reſolve by Gods grace aſſiſting us, to be Hanged upon Gibbits or to be Burned at a Stake to ſuffer the worſt of deaths and dangers, rather than to incorporate our ſelves into ſuch a Diabolical Corporation:—6thly, He that ſhall Communicate with the good men of the Churches of Diſſenters ſhall certainly Communicate with as good men as any are, I will not preſume to ſay under the Copes of Heaven, but in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> If we Refer to thoſe good men of the Miniſtry, then for excelling of Natural Parts, profoundneſs of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Evenneſs of Temper, Generoſity of Principles, moſt admirable Sermons and Doctrines, Holineſs of Life and largeneſs of Charity beſides what Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation be given of the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> in general, for a proof and demonſtration of theſe laſt particulars, I do humbly and ſollemnly appeal to all ſuch ſober &amp; wiſe perſons that frequent the Diſſenters Aſſemblies, and are not yet joyned in Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with any of them, 2dly, I appeal to the wiſe ſober and judicious Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to the Learned as well as unto the Unlearned, who have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny intimacy or good acquaintance with them, 3dly, I refer to thoſe Books formerly and lately Printed by the Leaders and Miniſters of the Diſſenters, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered under the names of Independents, Presbyterians and Baptiſts,—I know it will be objected, that many of the Nonconformiſt Preachers are not learned men
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63584:9"/> unto which I anſwer firſt, That many of the Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> tho' they have been long at the beſt Schools, yet they are not over Learned, and ſo it may be truly ſaid of ſome of the Diſſenters.—2dly, That the Excellency of Religion, &amp; the underſtanding of Divine Myſteries, doth not depend upon Humane Learning. 3dly, They have paſſed the orderly approbation of Chriſtian Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, and the approbation of their Miniſters and are ſuch as have in a good meaſure learned the Holy Scriptures, which is able to make them wiſe unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, both for themſelves, and how to inſtruct others. 7thly, If it be dangerous and unſafe to Communicate with the Diſſenters, it muſt be becauſe they are no Churches at all, or at beſt but Antichriſtian Churches; but Antichriſtian they cannot be, becauſe they have Renounced the power and headſhip of Antichriſt, and in their conſtant Doctrine &amp; Practice keep up &amp; defend a ſeparation from, &amp; deteſtation of him Thus have I humbly returned the Pamphleteer's, Arguments ſuch as they be, upon his own head, but chiefly deſire they may reach his heart, that ſo upon a better conſideration of them, he may learn better things from them, for the preſent and future good of his poor ſoul.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Envy, poyſonous Envy, is demonſtrated at a high rate in the ſaid Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet againſt the poor Diſſenters, rendring of them as high enemies to God, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable abuſers of God, as ſhall be conſidred in the following particulars, page 9. in that he ſaith that the greateſt number of the Diſſenters do hold principles dangerouſly heretical, and moſt abominable abuſing of the moſt Holy and Bleſſed <hi>God,</hi> ſuch as indeed do no leſs in their direct Conſequences then Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>god him, by making of him the greateſt Author of Miſchief in the world and the Tranſactor of ſuch profound folly as was never yet found in any weak and ſilly mortal under Heaven, and all this by thoſe idle dreams in &amp; about his peremptory and eternal Decrees.—2dly, Page 10 the Pamphleteer doth further foam out his envy againſt the Diſſenters, in a way of nonſenſical ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, ſaying, O Excellent and Stupendious Folly! Neither is this all, but indeed the leaſt part of what they impute to the beſt of beings, <hi>viz.</hi> The Angels falling from Heaven by Trangreſſion to be Devils, <hi>Cain</hi> killing of <hi>Abel, Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> Murdering the men of <hi>Sechem, Davids</hi> Committing of Adultery, and murdering of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah, Judas</hi> Betraying Chriſt the <hi>Jews</hi> by wicked hands to ſlay him, <hi>Solomon</hi> to have a thouſand Whores, all the Roman Emperors and Popes to make bloody ſhambles of the Chriſtian World, that when they are drunk, lye, <hi>ſwear,</hi> blaſpheem, challenge God to damn them, when they Rob, Steal, ſhed blood, are ſent to <hi>Newgate</hi> and <hi>Tyburn</hi> for Fellons, poor miſerable Wretches, they could no ways help it, and yet that they ſhould be Hanged here, and damned hereafter, for doing it, although by the ſame God forbidden and commanded to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with the greateſt threats and ſeriouſneſs; and he concludeth all theſe words and things thus—If there can be ſuch a profound Diſſembler, ſuch a deceitful Worker, ſuch an horrible Contriver, ſuch an Evil Ordainer and miſchevious Author, that is not a great and mighty Devil, I will confeſs my ſelf miſtaken.—Unto which I Reply humbly and modeſtly thus.</p>
            <p>1. What had this Envious Wretch a mind to expoſe the Diſſenters to the rage and fury of thoſe that neither fear the Laws of God, nor the good Laws of the Realm, that are for the reſtraining and puniſhing of men for groſs wickedneſs? now this horrible abuſing of the moſt high God, as he calleth it, is charged upon all thoſe Diſſenters, that hold the Doctrine of Gods particular E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of ſome of mankind to eternal ſalvation.—2dly, What kindneſs hath this Pamphleteer ſhewed to, or what ſervice hath he done for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by his former deſperate diſcourſe? for as much as it is well known that the Doctrine of particular Election, is the Principle and Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and has been highly maintained by the moſt famous Miniſters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63584:10"/> thoſe of a contrary mind, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as are called <hi>Arminians;</hi> and though ſome of the Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and ſome of the Diſſenters, do oppoſe the aforeſaid Doctrine, yet as they are men of good humanity they have more manners, and as they are men of Chriſtianity they have more grace, then to uſe ſuch blaſphemous expreſſions, and to draw ſuch diabolical Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning the Profeſſors of ſuch Election, and the Electing Gracious God. But no marvel that he whoſe Principle is, that men may fall from true and ſaving grace, ſhould himſelf fall from ſeeming grace.—3dly, And now I will humbly offer my opinion and faith concerning Election.—Firſt I do believe that God from all Eternity, or before the World begun, hath Elected ſome of the Children of men unto Eternal Salvation, and in due time hath and doth and will bleſs them with ſaving Converſion in order thereunto, Eph. 1.4. <hi>According as he hath Choſen us in him before the Foundation of the World, that we ſhould be holy and without blame before him in love,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.13. <hi>But we are bound to give thanks to God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways for you Brethren, becauſe God hath from the beginning Choſen you to Salvation, through Sanstification of the Spirit and belief of the Truth,</hi>—2dly, I believe that God in his gracious Decree of this Election hath fixed upon every one of the particular perſons that ſhould afterward be eternaly ſaved, Pſalm 139. verſ. 16. <hi>Thine eyes did ſee my Subſtance yet being unperfect, and in thy Book all my Members were written, which in continuance were faſhioned, when as yet there was none of them;</hi> which Scripture muſt be underſtood of the Members of <hi>Davids</hi> natural Body, or of Chriſt's Myſtical Body; if of <hi>Davids</hi> natural Body, then we may ſurely ſay, God hath not a leſs regard to, and care of Chriſts myſtical Body, but doth cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly know all the Members thereof, and hath them down in his Book, whilſt as yet they are not viſible in the world, 2 Tim. 2.19. <hi>Nevertheleſs the Foundation of God standeth ſure, having this Seal, the Lord knoweth them that are his;</hi> Now God doth not only know them that are his when Converted, but before Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Conſider thoſe words, John 10.14. I <hi>am the good Shepherd, and know my Sheep, and am known of mine.</hi> Verſe 16. <hi>Other Sheep</hi> I <hi>have which are not of this Fold, them alſo</hi> I <hi>muſt bring, and they ſhall hear my voice, and there ſhall be one Fold and one Sheepherd.</hi> Verſe 26. <hi>But ye believe not becauſe ye are not of my Sheep, as</hi> I <hi>ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</hi> Verſe 27. <hi>My Sheep hear my voice, and I know them and they follow me:</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion and Salvation of perticular perſons were both in God together, as the act of his infinite mercy and rich grace, before the world began.</p>
            <p>Conſider that Word well, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Who hath ſaved us and called us with an Holy Calling, not according to our Works, but according to his own purpoſe and grace, which was given us in Chriſt, before the World began.</hi> And conſider alſo that Word, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.5. <hi>Even ſo at this preſent time alſo there is a remnant accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Election of Grace:</hi> and verſ. 7. <hi>The Election hath obtained it, and the reſt were blinded.</hi>—Fourthly, I believe that as ſaving <hi>Grace here,</hi> and <hi>Eternal Glory</hi> hereafter unto all them that are ſaved, is Gods undeſerved mercy; Even ſo alſo thoſe that are ſuffered to go on in their Sins here, and ſhall be damned for their Sins hereafter, is unto them but Gods deſerved Juſtice.—Fifthly, I believe that God hath not laid any Neceſſity upon men to be Wicked, for God doth not force any man to ſin; but man being created upright, abode not in that State, but ſought out many Inventions, as in <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.29. The whole Lump of Mankind is involved in a ſinful ſtate, and ſo is become unable of himſelf to do any thing that may ſave himſelf; for the very Saints of God are not ſaved by works of Righteouſneſs which they have wrought; ſee <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Not by Works of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs which we have wrought, but according to his Mercy he hath ſaved us, by the Waſhing of Regeneration, and Renewing of the Holy Ghost.</hi>—Sixthly, I do howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver believe that though not any man can make himſelf ſo good as to be ſaved by it, yet moſt men may be abundantly better then they are, by improving the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63584:11"/> Light of Nature, and thoſe Natural parts they have, wherein ſome excel others, together with an improvement of the common Mercies and Bleſſings of God, and more eſpecially by attending upon the meanes of grace, and may hereby e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape thoſe black and bloody Crimes, that the Pamphleteer doth moſt baſely innumerate, and may alſo be in a hopeful way of Converſation, and ſo of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, like the poor man that lay at the pool of <hi>Betheſda, John.</hi> 5.3.5. <hi>Who though he was not able of himſelf to go in the Pool,</hi> he lay in the way of a cure; but if men will follow Wickedneſs with greedineſs, they are in the ready way of Damnation, without any ground of hope for Salvation.—Seventhly, I believe that Salvation of Sinners is founded altogether upon Chriſt, and laid up only and alone in Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> In his perſon as God and Man, in his perfect Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, in his painful Sufferings in the garden, and upon the croſs, in his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from the dead, in his Aſcenſion into Heaven, and in his Interceſſion in Heaven, and ſhall be moſt fully compleated at the Reſurrection of the dead, and the ſecond coming of Chriſt, when the vile bodies of Saints ſhall be like the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious body of Jeſus Chriſt, and <hi>ſo ſhall ever</hi> be with the Lord. Eighthly, I believe that if <hi>God</hi> of his own free grace and rich mercy had not made the Eternal ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of ſome particular perſons infallibly certain, by decreeing their ſaving converſion before time, and bleſſing of them with it in time, it would have been hazardous whether any ſinners ſhould have been ſaved; for as much as a very great multitude of mankind, yea and many that have ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>air way for Salvation, and have miſt of it, by the ſame Reaſons eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular perſon might have miſt of it alſo.—9thly, I believe that for as much as Sinners in general have deſerved Damnation, and none of them able to give Divine Juſtice ſatisfaction for themſelves, the great and glorious God may mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie his Mercy upon ſome, and glorifie his Juſtice upon others, as ſeemeth good, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Inſinite Wiſdom; ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.22. <hi>What if God willing to ſhew his wrath and make his power known, endured with much Long Suffering the Veſſels of wrath fitted for deſtruction.</hi> Verſe 23. <hi>And that he might make known the Riches of his glory on the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of mercy, which he had afore prepared unto glory:</hi> alſo ſee Rom. 9.20. <hi>Nay, but, O man, who art thou that repliest againſt God?</hi> And let the Pamphleteer conſider what he hath done in ſpeaking ſo reproachfully of the Servants of the Living God, both amongſt the Diſſenters and the Church of <hi>England</hi> alſo, and in drawing ſuch blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Concluſions concerning God, from their Principles.—Fifthly, High and deſperate Rayling is in the ſaid Pamphlet: Take notice of page 11. in theſe words, <q rend="inline">Now if a ſound &amp; true notion of God be the firſt and foundation principle of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and conſequently of a true Church, then ſuch as have it not, but the manifeſt con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rary, can be no true Church, becauſe upon a wicked &amp; falſe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, ſuch as I am ſure is among the Sectaries; and if ſuch a villanous Body of people is the beſt and true Church, that even in their firſt principles thus bloodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly murder their Maker, in his moſt admirable Attributes of Wiſdom, Holineſs and Goodneſs, I do wonder what kind of people the <hi>world</hi> is.</q> 
               <hi>And then over again he has theſe words,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">VVhat ſhall we ſay of ſuch monſters, that murder God their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker? ſhall we join with them as a pious Church?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now conſider a few Queries upon this bloody matter.</p>
            <p>Firſt, What has the poor Wretch forgot, what Work he was about, <hi>viz.</hi> High pleading for the Church of <hi>England</hi> as the only Church of God in the <hi>World,</hi> and now ſtrike deadly ſtrokes at her heart through the tender ſides of the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, in a moſt Abominable abuſing both the one and the other about the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Decrees of God, as if their Opinions in thoſe things were an in-let to all the moſt Abominable Wickedneſs that is in this World, and a murdering of God our maker to boot!—2dly. What doth the man think that the Church of <hi>England</hi> will receive ſuch a <hi>Child</hi> as a true Son, who moſt boldly affirmeth that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63584:12"/> ſuch as hold Gods decrees to be unalterable cannot be a true Church of God, but a villanous body of People; when it is well known that the Diſſenters, who are <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> do very well agree about the Eternal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of God. 3dly. What has the child a mind to call his Mother Whore, as ſoon as he is born? O what a Monſter is this, that after two or three times ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hath got ſharp Teeth, and long Nailes, and moſt unnaturally falls a biting and ſcratching his Mothers tender Breaſt! Its well known that the Breaſt of the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth afford the ſame good Milk as is among thoſe Diſſenters that he doth ſo highly and bitterly rail againſt, <hi>viz.</hi> The Doctrine of Gods un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterable Decrees concerning the children of men.—4thly, What is the man mad in his mind, becauſe the Proteſtant Diſſenters do not believe that the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God is not ſuch a one as he is, who hath altered, changed, and ſhu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ed, in his Opinions Principles and Practiſes about Religion? the Lord rebuke his Soul with that Word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. <hi>Thou thoughtest I was altogether ſuch a one as thy ſelf:</hi> And now let it be ſoberly conſidered how the Pamphletere hath ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf, in railing againſt the poor Diſſenters, now in the time of <hi>their</hi> Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, even as <hi>Shimei</hi> did rail againſt poor <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7. <hi>Come out, come out, thou bloody man, and thou man of Belial:</hi> Now mark this mans Words, of the Diſſenters, <q rend="inline">A villanous body of People, that in their firſt and main Principle thus bloodily murder their Maker in his moſt admirable Attributes, and uſeth the Words of <hi>Jacob, Curſed be their anger for it was fierce, and their Wrath for it was Cruel, O my Soul come not into their ſecret; unto their Aſſembly: mine honour be not thou united,</hi> what ſhall we ſay of ſuch Monſters that murder God their maker, ſhall we join with them as a pious Church?</q> Now theſe Diſſenters that he meaneth are thoſe called <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> and what their Principles are, is well known to, and approved of, by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> except it be ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Clergymen called <hi>Arminians</hi> as alſo ſome Diſſenters are, who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding do abhor this Abominable Stupendious Railery, and though they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in their Opinions about the Decrees of God, yet they have charitable Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of each other, and a cordial love to each other, each party knowing that there is a Godly care on both ſides to maintain a Godly Converſation in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and make ſure of Salvation for themſelves.—But as for the Pamphletere who is a ſhame to himſelf and others, let him read his Tranſgreſſion and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.19. <hi>Thou givest thy mouth to Evil, and thy tongue frameth deceit.</hi> Verſ. 20. <hi>Thou ſittest and ſpeakest againſt thy Brother, thou ſlandereſt thine own Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Son.</hi> Verſ. 21. <hi>Theſe things haſt thou done, and I kept ſilence: thou thoughteſt I was altogether ſuch a one as thy ſelf; but I will reprove thee, and ſet them in Order before thine Eyes.</hi>—Sixthly, Forgery is in the ſaid Pamphlet at an abominable rate, in that the Pamphleteer doth heap up many particulars which he cannot prove, therefore they muſt be charged upon himſelf, as matter forged and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in his own <hi>Working Pate,</hi> Conſider page 12. where he formeth ſeveral que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and Anſwers according to his own mind; which take as followeth.—<q rend="inline">Firſt, Would they have the Arch-biſhops down? <hi>Yes</hi> no doubt. Secondly, Would they have the reſt of the Biſhops down? <hi>Yes.</hi> Thirdly, Would they have the beſt Clergy about the City and Subburbs down? <hi>Yes.</hi> Fourthly, Would they have all the Clergy in <hi>England</hi> down? <hi>Yes.</hi> Fifthly, Would they have all the Eccleſiaſtical Revenues, <hi>viz.</hi> The Unlawful Maintenance by Tythes, down? <hi>Yes.</hi> Sixthly, Would they have all the Schools of Learning down? <hi>Yes,</hi> becauſe the Language of the Beaſt that oppoſes the Spirits Teachings, ſet forth by <hi>Samuel How,</hi> comes from thence. Seventhly, Would they have the Laws for maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the poor down? <hi>Yes.</hi>
               </q> From which particulars conſider theſe things. Firſt conſider how like a <hi>Child</hi> the pamphleteer doth behave himſelf, who not being able to throw ſticks at a <hi>live Cock,</hi> makes a <hi>paper Cock,</hi> and then taketh great pains
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63584:13"/> to throw it down. Secondly, Conſider how hard he is put to it to make up the number of ſeven folliſh Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in making two about the Biſhops, and two about the Clergy. Thirdly, Conſider his baſe deſign, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Repreſent the Diſſenters Obnoxious and Odious to the Biſhops and Clergy, and to ſtir up hatred and rage in them, againſt the poor Diſſenters, who are already under Sufferings in this City and many parts of <hi>England;</hi> and hereby he hath plainly diſcovered, that he is for the ſame thing, that he ſaith the Adverſaries have been long la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring about, (ſee Page 2.) <hi>viz.</hi> to divide the Proteſtants, and to put the Proteſtant Clergy upon Perſecuting the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, and it is hereby evident, rather then there ſhall be any empty ſpace in Perſecution, what is wanting by the Old Adverſaries he will ſet his helping hand to ſupply, by doing farther miſchief in ſtirring up the Clergy againſt the poor Diſſenters, and ſo much more divide thoſe that ſhould be in greater Unity, becauſe they are agreed in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt things of Chriſtianity, and all in the ſame danger of the Old Enemy of Proteſtants, <hi>viz. Rome;</hi> and thus the Pamphleteer is guilty of thoſe Evils mentioned in <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Theſe ſix things the Lord hateth, yea ſeven are an Abomination to him,</hi> Verſ. 17. <hi>A proud look, a lying tongue, and hands that ſhed innocent blood,</hi> Verſ. 18. <hi>An Heart that deviſeth Wicked immaginations, feet that he ſwift running to Miſchief, a falſe Witneſs that ſpeaketh lyes, and him that ſoweth diſcord among Brethren.</hi>—Fourthly, Conſider whether the Pamphleteer hath any juſt cauſe to Write and Print thus of the Diſſenters in general, and therefore I will take a brief Notice of his particulars: Firſt Concerning Arch-biſhops, and Biſhops: though the Diſſenters cannot account them to be ſuch Biſhops as were in the primitive Church, becauſe they cannot find any mention of Arch-biſhops or Lord biſhops in the new Teſtament, yet for as much as it pleaſeth the King, and is agreeable to the Conſtitution of the Government, the Diſſenters are very well contented to live under ſuch Government in all peaceable manner, and give that Reverence and Reſpect to them as becometh Chriſtianity and Humanity, and then I think the Biſhops have no cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the Diſſenters, as being any abuſers of them; and for my own part I am apt to think that if the Kingdom had not them, there might be worſe in their Room.—Secondly, Concerning the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy, and their Maintenance, it is well known, that the Diſſenters in City and Countrey have a venerable eſteem of ſuch as are known to be men of good Learning, good Natural Parts, good Preachers, and eſpecially men of Spiritual Goodneſs. <hi>viz.</hi> Men of Godly Converſations: as for their Maintenance both in City and Country, it is Chearfully paid, not as an Act of force, but as their Right by Law, as other things are the Right of other men by the ſame Law; and it is but a few Diſſenters that muſt be excepted in this matter, compared with the whole body of Diſſenters throughout the Kingdom: and <hi>they</hi> are deemed by their friends to be more ſcrupulous then they need or ought to be; and beſides it is well known that thoſe Pariſh Miniſters who are obliging to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhoners, do not onely Receive their Due by Law, from the Diſſenters, but do alſo partake of their love.—Fourthly, As concerning the Schooles of Learning in both Univerſities, it is well known that Learning was highly incouraged, and Sobriety was well maintained in thoſe times wherein ſuch as are now Diſſenters were concerned both as Heads and Schollars in thoſe Noble Schools; and the Diſſenters do now rejoice in the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of Learning in both Univerſities, and in other good Schools, of the Kingdom; and yet Diſſenters have good cauſe to believe, that though humane Learning is a very good thing, and although men may arrive to high degrees in it, yet they may be very ignorant of Divine Miſteries, which is indeed the Teachings of the Spirit of God; it was not for want of Humane Learning that <hi>Nicodemus a Ruler and Maſter in Iſrael did not underſtand the new and Spiritual birth, when he ſaid, How can a man be born when he is Old? Can he enter the ſecond time into his Mothers Womb, and be born again?</hi> John. 3.4. Neither was it for want of humane Learning <hi>that the Greeks did count the Preaching of Salvation by a Crucified Chriſt, Fooliſhneſs,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23. Nor is it not for want of Humane Learning that the Jeſuites and other great Schollars brought up in the Popiſh Schools do not turn Proteſtants: and it is baſely done of the Pamphleteer, to reflect upon Mr. <hi>Samuel How,</hi> who hath been in his Grave a great number of years, who though he was but a mean man in the world, he deſerved great honour, as a man of good natural parts, and an able Preacher of Gods Word; a gracious Soul, and a man of holy life and Converſation.—5thly, Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Laws for maintainance of the poor in the ſeveral Pariſhes of <hi>England,</hi> of which the Pamphleteer ſaith the Diſſenters would faln have them down alſo, this ſeems as if he would ſtir up a Spirit of Rage in the Poor againſt the Diſſenters, to fall about their Ears, as being the worſt of the Poor's enemies, but bleſſed be God it is well known throughout this Kingdom, that the Diſſenters do moſt Cheerfully pay the Pariſh Taxes for the ſupply of the Poor, and rejoice that there is ſuch a proviſion made for them, beſides being Charitable to them other ways.</p>
            <p>Thus have I briefly replyed unto this part of the mans forgery, in Charging the poor Diſſenters in general with things of which they are not guilty. But hearken, Brethren, here i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a very large emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſpace, and ſeeing Nature abhors a vacuity, conſider what proviſion the Pamphleteer has made to fill up again in the room of thoſe things before Rehearſed,—Firſt you ſhall in the room of the two Arch-biſhops, (<hi>viz. Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, and York.</hi>) have a Tinker, and a Taylor, men of great confidence and long ſtanding,—2dly, For the four great Biſhopricks of <hi>London, Winchester, Eli,</hi> and <hi>Durham,</hi> you ſhall have a Water man, a Shoomaker, a Coffee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and a Hat-dreſſer; and for the other Biſhops and the Glergy about the City and Suburbs of <hi>London,</hi> you ſhall have men of an inferiour rank. And then the poor deſperate Wretch contrives how this may be made known to <hi>France, Germany</hi> and the Low Countries; and all theſe things he chargeth upon the Diſſenters, (page 13.) as their contrivance, to make ſuch an alteration in the Government. And now I will moſt humbly and modeſtly reply, and therein ſolemnly appeal to all the Church-men of <hi>England,</hi> of what degree ſoever, who have any conſiderable knowledge of and acquaintance with the Diſſentrs and their Principles, that the aforeſaid Charge is moſt notoriouſly and abominably falſe, for as much as it is well known throughout the Kingdom, that ſuch perſons as are before mentioned are not at all deſirous of ſuch things, it being quite contrary to their known and profeſſed Principles to have ſuch Eccleſiaſtical Dignities conferred upon them; and yet they are ſuch friends to the preſent Government, as it is Eſtabliſhed by Law, that they can freely when ever His Majeſty ſhall have occaſion, venture their lives to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his Perſon and Crown, to defend Arch-biſhops &amp; the reſt of the Biſhops, to defend all the Clergy &amp; the Church of <hi>England,</hi> againſt the Pope and all his Cardinals, againſt the Jeſuites and all the Popiſh Party, they being Enemies to the King and whole Kingdom, as it is a Proteſtant Kingdom; and though the Diſſenters may differ from the Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome things from one another, yet the Church of <hi>England</hi> and the Diſſenters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the King &amp; Kingdom, &amp; I alſo who am not aſhamed to own my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſelf ſuch a Loyal Subject to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> King, ſuch a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> fore is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63584:14"/> according to 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.2. and let the Pamphleteer lay to heart thoſe words, Pſalm 52. verſe 3. <hi>Thou loveſt evil more than good, and Lying more than to ſpeak Righteouſneſs:</hi> verſe 4. <hi>Thou loveſt all devouring words, O thou De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful Tongue! O Abominable and Stupendious Forgery!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Hypocriſy is plainly demonſtrated in the ſaid Pamphlet: A brief account take as followeth in ſeveral particulars: Firſt, In the Pamphleteers pretending to find fault with Perſecution, in page 2. and yet reckoneth it with other good things, as a means to bring Diſſenters to Church, (ſee page 1.) 2dly, In his pretending to plead high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the Church of <hi>England</hi> all along in his Pamphlet, as being the only Church, and the Clergy the only men in the whole world for Chriſtianity, and yet doth baſely inſinuate a Confedracy between them and the Papiſts, as being influenced by the Papiſts to Perſecute the Diſſenters, (ſee page 2.) 3dly, In that he doth baſely reflect upon the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for Erecting ſo many new Meeting-places, when it is well known, that he would have been heartily glad to have had one himſelf, ſo as to have been ſet as Chief Preacher and Governour over ſome Separate Congregation; either a new or old Meeting-place, would have ſerved to ſtop his mouth with a good maintenance; but miſſing of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, he is ſo fallen into vexation, that he doth not care what he foameth out againſt the poor Diſſenters, (page 12) 4thly, In that he chargeth the Diſſenters with the total neglect of that great Moral Duty to pay unto God the tenth of their Encreaſe. Now that the tenth of Increaſe was once payable to God by reaſon of a Precept in the <hi>Old Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> I grant, but how it will be proved a moral duty flowing from a Moral Law written in all mens hearts, I do not underſtand; but here is the mans hypocriſy, that he chargeth that upon others, when himſelf will have a very hard task to prove that he hath made it his own duty in the performance of it; conſider Mat. 7.5. <hi>Thou Hypocrite, firſt caſt out the Beam out of thine own Eye, then ſhalt thou ſee clearly to caſt out the Moat out of thy Brothers Eye;</hi> and yet it is well known that the Diſſenters do make Conſcience to ſerve God with their Subſtance,—5thy. In that he concludeth (page 14.) that if the Diſſenters are not the True Church, nor the Church of <hi>England</hi> the True Church, then it muſt be the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and doth not at all deny the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be the True Church, as he hath denyed the Diſſenters. 6thly, His Hypocriſy will further appear (page 14.) in that he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth favourably and lovingly of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in theſe very words, <hi>Though, Sir, I do love the People of the Romiſh Communion well</hi>—But harken Brethren, what a double faced man is this, yea, what a double hearted man is this? as doth appear by his double tongue, in pleading ſo highly for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and at laſt to ſay, <hi>If the Diſſenters nor the Church of</hi> England <hi>be the true Church, then the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>muſt, or elſe where ſhall we find it</hi>—7thly, Hypocriſy doth further appear, in that he ſaith, <hi>Tho' he loveth that Church well, yet he is loth it ſhould be counted the true Church, becauſe it may be inconvenient upon divers accounts;</hi> and then he reckoneth up ſome politick conſiderations reſpecting outward damages, <hi>viz.</hi> Then we ſhall be in danger of a Popiſh Parliament, then all our beſt Miniſters will be turned out of the beſt Benefices, the Writ <hi>de Heretico Comburendo</hi> will be reſtored, &amp; thereby the beſt Defenders of our Religion againſt Popery be forced to pledge <hi>Philpot, Ridley, Granmer</hi> &amp; <hi>Latimer</hi> in a warm Cup of <hi>Smithfield</hi> Flames, then all our married Clergy moſt be reputed Fornicators, their Wives Whores, their Children Baſtards, then our Noble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Gentry will loſe a great part of their Eſtates, which was formerly Church-Lands, then will <hi>London</hi> much abate in in its Trade and Grandeur, then all our Proteſtant Merchants will be put to flight into other Countries to ſave their own and the lives of their beloved Ladies, then <hi>England</hi> will be inſlaved by a red Coat Army; beſides many do fear if Popery comes in, there will be yet many more places ſet on ſire to the prejudice of the whole Kingdom; and amongſt all theſe things he doth not forget to ſpeak faintly in behalf of the Common-Prayer-Book, ſaying, Then our good Book of Common-Prayer will be changed, which I think few or none can make a better. Harken, Brethren, here is not one word to bewail the loſs of the Holy Bible, in which there is an infallible diſcovery of Gods Holy Will, and our Holy Duties; not a word to bewail the loſs of the moſt powerful Preachers upon the account of their being Inſtruments in the hand of God to Convert poor ſouls, he only ſheweth a little unwillingneſs that the beſt Miniſters ſhould be turned out of the beſt Benefices, and not a word to bewail the loſs of the holy Sacrament, and to have inſtead thereof that abominable Idol called the Sacrament of the Altar. Harken Brethren yet further, notwithſtanding this Pamphleteer doth know all theſe miſeries that may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>end the faithful Proteſtants, yet he has the confidence to ſay <hi>he loveth thoſe of the Romiſh Communion;</hi> and doth not ſay, he cannot in conſcience own them to be a true Church at all, but ſaith he is loath it ſhould be accounted a true Church <hi>in England,</hi> and that onely becauſe it is inconvenient; and doth not deny thoſe of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be a true Church at <hi>Rome,</hi> and in other Countries; and he hath left himſelf an empty ſpace to be filled up with Conformity unto thoſe of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Communion, when he ſhall find a Conveniency. O Abominable Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy in the Pamphleteer, to undertake the Cauſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt the Proteſtant Diſſenters, and at laſt ſpeak faintly of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſpeaketh favourably of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſpeak lovingly of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> yea ſaith he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth that Party well, even that Church who is the implacable enemy of the poor Church of <hi>England,</hi> and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to put out the Eyes, and pluck out the Heart, and Cut off the Head of the Proteſtant Church of <hi>England,</hi> as hath been made evident by the late Damnable Popiſh Plot. Therefore let all true Proteſtant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be at peace one with another, and be in love one to another, and joyn head and heart and hand together againſt this bloody Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, that has ſtained many Countries with Proteſtant Blood. And let all ſorts of Proteſtants beware of a Falſe Brother, and let the Church of <hi>England</hi> beware of a Falſe <hi>CHILD</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Prov. 27.8.</bibl>
                  <p>As a Bird that wandereth from her Neſt, ſo is a man that wandereth from his place.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
